hello everyone great you can see me
Daniel says loud and clear so excellent
okay well thanks guys for tuning in and
and again for offering the support for
the continued operation of my youtube
channel so let's get going
it's good to see all of you and so I've
got a set of questions here I can see
the the live stream as well the live
chat so that's great all right let's try
this one what's an effective way to
figure out how to match your career with
your temperament how can you determine
if a job is a good fit or a terrible
mistake let's start with the first one
what's a good way of
what's an effective way to figure out
how to match your career with your
temperament well the first thing you do
obviously that you have to do is to
understand your temperament to some
degree and so the best way to deal with
that is to get yourself assessed using a
good big five instrument there's many of
them online we're going to be setting up
a website within the next month that
will enable people to do use a tool that
a student of mine call Andy young who's
now a professor at the University of
Minnesota and I and some other
co-authors developed back in in I think
it was 2007 called the big five aspect
scale and it breaks the big five down
into ten aspects and we'll have a
version of that online I hope by the end
of July that's the plan that will enable
people to get a read of their
temperament that will tell them how
extroverted they are how high they are a
negative emotion or neuroticism how
agreeable how conscientious and how open
but it'll break each of those traits
down into two aspects so extraversion
breaks into enthusiasm and assertiveness
neuroticism breaks into withdrawal and
volatility agreeableness breaks down
into politeness and compassion
conscientiousness into orderliness and
industrious and openness into openness
proper which is something like
creativity and interest in ideas and so
the first thing you have to know is what
your temperament is the second thing you
should probably know and we'll probably
add this functionality to the system at
some point is what your intelligence
level is what your IQ is because the the
higher your IQ the better suited you are
for jobs whose demands change rapidly
and most so those are complex jobs and
simple jobs are the jobs where you can
learn something and then you can run it
as an algorithm you can just repeat it
over and over and those jobs of course
are becoming more and more scarce so you
need to know what your temperament is
and then you need to know the
temperamental demands of the job
now most jobs are mastered with a
combination of intelligence and
conscientiousness but the other
temperamental factors play a moderating
role so for example extroverted people
tend to be entertainer types and highly
social
and so if you're interested for example
in if you're extroverted then a career
in sales is something that you might
consider a career that involves a lot of
public communication and interaction
with groups whereas you're an introvert
you're going to work you're going to
want to work a lot more you're going to
be suited to work honest in a solitary
manner a lot more if you're agreeable
you're going to be suited for taking
care of people if you're disagreeable
then you're a tough bargainer and a hard
ago she ater and and litigators for
example lawyers are often low in
agreeableness so if you're conscientious
well that tends to be a very good trait
for any kind of managerial and
administrative job and for for for
simpler jobs as well it's a great
predictor of military prowess for
example if you're high in openness then
you're gonna want a creative career and
that might make you an entrepreneur or a
musician or an artist about or something
like that that's often very very
difficult to monetize but one of the
funny things about openness is that if
you're high in openness it's not that
helpful at the bottom of hierarchies
because you're basically expected at the
bottom of most hierarchies to act more
or less like a functionary but it
becomes of critical importance at the
top of hierarchy so it's a personality
trait whose utility can really kick in
in the later stages of your career
because in really complex positions
where things are changing dynamically
you need to have a high intelligence and
you also need to be creative so how can
you determine if a job is a good fit or
a terrible mistake
ha well I would say you can tell if it's
a terrible mistake if you dread going
and also if you're working hard and
doing what you're supposed to and you're
not being rewarded for it or and there's
no chance for advancement so that those
are good reasons to to leave so alright
truck plain says just wanted to tell you
that you're the first person to actually
make me read books I have a background
in math and engineering lots of formulas
and equations keep up your work well
good work truck playing there's some
real utility in reading books and I'm
glad that you found the
I'm glad that you figured out why it's
necessary to do that so that's that's uh
that's I'm very happy to hear that
Oliver Connor says it's definitely worth
doing the humanities it gives you a
skill set you can apply anywhere that's
actually worth elaborating on a little
bit because I do believe that classical
humanities education is at the core of
the proper university curriculum and you
might say well what's the utility for
example in studying philosophy and
literature but that's not exactly the
right way to look at it the utility of
humanities education at least in
principle is that it teaches you first
of all how to be civilized and educated
so that you become aware of the major
cultural works that every educated
person needs to be aware of in order to
operate properly at a high level of
functionality in the world and what
you'll find is that as you get older and
you climb hierarchies of competence that
broader and broader educational
familiarity is demanded of you but more
importantly education in the humanities
is designed to teach you how to think
and to speak and to formulate arguments
and because what you're doing in complex
positions almost always involves the
identification of problems and their
articulations so that you can frame the
problem then a description of a
potential set of solutions and then the
communication of those set of solutions
to a wide variety of people in a manner
that can help them obtain a consensus
and work together those set those skills
are absolutely crucial when you're doing
anything that's a real difficulty and so
the humanities education is
extraordinarily important as it as a
consequence of that here's a question PS
Jay's final stage of morality was he who
can who he who can create the rules
would you please provide an example of
what that means yeah I can I can
it says I'm having trouble I can't get
the rest of it but can you can you
please provide an example of what that
means well look at at a lower stage of
Piaget and development let's say where
you're a child and you learn to play a
game you're going to determine morality
on the basis of how well you as a player
adhere to the rules
now at the point of development above
that you start to understand that well
the rules were actually a human creation
in in their original form and that what
that means is that when it's necessary
the rules can be adjusted think about
the Harry Potter series I mean one of
the things that characterizes Harry and
his friends is that they're and Hermione
is a really good example of this is that
they're sufficiently disciplined I mean
she happens to be really disciplined and
are perfectly capable of following the
rules but also make exceptions when
that's necessary and it's the fact that
they can step beyond the rules when that
becomes necessary that actually makes
them the heroes of the adventure because
it's very difficult to set up a
situation where you can always act
perfectly only by following the rules
because it's very difficult to delineate
out a rule set that's sufficiently
comprehensive so it'll cover every
eventuality so that's the that's the
upshot on that women have a tendency to
prefer bad men higher in dark triad
traits how come the Bible describes a
mode of being as associated with nice
guy traits which contradict that okay
well I take issue with both elements of
that actually I don't believe that women
do have a tendency to prefer bad men
higher in dark triad traits they may
have a tendency to be more erratically
attracted to men who are capable of
manifesting dominance and aggression I
think the evidence for that is
relatively clear and I don't think the
Bible at all just describes a mode of
being as associated with nice guy traits
I don't know that may be how it's
classically taught for example because
Christ is often presented especially and
more simple-minded
vary variants and I'm not being
pejorative about that precisely as the
ultimate in nice guys but I don't think
that that's true at all that's a
reasonable characterization at all if
you read the Gospel accounts because he
was someone who was certainly capable of
saying very very harsh things to people
and was also identified very strongly as
a figure who was capable of using
judgment and distinguishing between what
was positive and what was
and that capacity for judgment is
something quite different than then then
the mere nice-guy compassion that would
be associated with high levels of trade
agreeableness so I think that the the
idea that the ideal that's put forward
in the biblical writings is something
like be harmless I think that's a real
miss reading of the text and I also
think that it's it's it's wrong because
harmless and good are not the same thing
at all in fact I think one of the best
ways of characterizing like a
higher-order morality and this is
something that Nietzsche talked about a
fair bit is that and Jung as well with
regards to the idea of integration of
the shadow is that someone whose morale
has the capability for violence and the
capability for aggression built in and
at hand but is also someone who's
perfectly capable of controlling that in
the civilized manner
and I think that you know I'm speaking
off-the-cuff here obviously but I think
that the the the attraction that some
women have for the for the sort of men
who are more likely to misbehave to act
in a delinquent manner and so forth is
partly their desire to be associated
with men who have the capacity for
aggression now the best of all possible
worlds is when that capacity for
aggression is civilized and held under
control but so I would say that one of
the things that men should do as they
mature is transform themselves into
monsters but also become civilized at
the same time and that's exactly what
you see in stories like Beauty and the
Beast where the the the ideal man starts
out as a beast and ends up civilized he
doesn't start out as a milksop wimp sort
of character who you know who poses no
threat to anyone and then becomes the
hero that isn't how it works although
there are stories of that kind of
development so which is the most
accessible of Carl Jung's books oh well
I wouldn't say any of them are
particularly accessible although modern
man in search of the soul is probably a
good one to start with that's modern
managed search of a soul I think modern
man in search of his soul anyways
it's modern man in search of a soul I
believe it's short and it's to the point
and and so that's a good introduction
which has been the most impactful to me
probably I on a IOM which is the second
volume the second volume of vol 9 of the
collected works which is an absolutely
amazing terrifying book which describes
it actually it actually it contains some
of Young's writings on the psychology of
astrology which are actually quite
interesting because he regarded
astrology as a millennia long as
millennia long fantasizing on the part
of the collective human imagination and
and spent a lot of time in analyzing the
content of that you might think about it
as a dream that was projected out into
the cosmos so what are your personal
strategies for consuming the news hmm
well you know it's funny for years I
haven't launched television news for
example and I don't read newspapers very
often either
I actually limit my exposure to the news
I read The Economist I used to read
Harper's Magazine I used to read The
Atlantic Monthly as well I thought they
were good periodicals although I think
both of them have collapsed quite
precipitously in recent years Harper's
maybe not so much how do I walk the line
between wanting to be informed while
avoiding the danger of cluttering your
mind well The Economist helps with that
I think it's actually going downhill to
some degree over recent years as well
but I definitely tell my clinical
clients very frequently especially if
they're depressed and feeling
overwhelmed just to limit their exposure
to to daily news particularly because if
something is only relevant the day that
it's published you could make the case
that it's not relevant at all which is
part of the reason why I like The
Economist because it only comes out
every week ER or two weeks depending on
your subscription and so it can only
cover things that have enough importance
to to be relevant over a timeframe that
exceeds a day so
all right so let's see what we've got in
the live stream here how do we revive
interest in the good mother archetype
well that's a good question I think it's
a good question in part because it isn't
really obvious to me that young women on
their society are told the truth about
what their lives are likely to be like
you know they're they're they're they're
taught both explicitly and implicitly
that their primary interest will be in
the pursuit of a dynamic career and
there's some real problems with that the
first is that the proportion of people
who will have a dynamic career in the
technical sense is actually quite low
because most people have jobs and not
careers and even in those jobs that
might be regarded as careers much of the
work that's done is job like I mean the
reason that people pay you to have a job
is often because you're required to do
things that you wouldn't do if you
weren't being paid and so we we
glamorize the role of career and confuse
jobs with careers and assume that most
people are going to end up with high end
careers and then we also assume that
most people even those who are qualified
to have high end careers are actually
the sort of people who would like to
have high end careers if they could and
that's also often not true so for
example I've worked very intensely with
a large population of female lawyers
usually see usually partners at large
law firms very very successful women
usually very attractive very intelligent
extraordinarily conscientious and the
sort of people who were outstanding in
high school and then outstanding as
undergraduates and then aced law school
and then did their articling perfectly
and then became associates and then
eventually entered the partner stream in
a large law firm and then became
partners and a huge proportion of them
wake up around 30 somewhere between 30
and 32 and notice they're 65 our day
and the incredibly competitive
environment that they happen to be in
and the fact that the demands of their
career are only going to accelerate as
they move forward I mean they're going
to make a lot of money but the demands
on their time of their career only going
to accelerate as they move forward and
decide quite rapidly that that's maybe
not what they want and the reason for
that is they also would like to have a
life they'd like to have a relationship
that they could attend to and they'd
like to have children and the truth of
the simple truth of the matter is is
that it's very very difficult to have a
truly high end career and have an
important relationship and have children
especially if there are two of you
trying to pursue that at the same time
it's very difficult and it's difficult
to have a high end career period and
it's also difficult to have a fully
functional family trying to combine
those sorts of things makes people who
are I mean I've seen people do it but
man they they push themselves right to
their limits and they usually have
limits that exceed the limits of typical
people so one of the things we can do
for example to revive interest in the
good mother archetype is to stop telling
lies to young women about what their
life is likely to be like because my
experience has been and you might think
I'm old-fashioned although I don't
really think I am by the way I think I'm
actually quite current and I pay a lot
of attention to what's going on around
me and my experience has been
overwhelmingly that high-caliber women
decide in their 30s that relationship
and family is the most important thing
in their life and I think the reason
that the fact that major law firms for
example have a really difficult time
holding on to their high-performing
women even though they bend over
backwards to do that is actually an
indication of exactly that and this
notion that it's a glass ceiling in some
sense that are stopping women from
advancing up the corporate ladder I
believe to be a truly erroneous as well
as dangerous and I don't think there's
real any really any evidence to support
that so all right Fraser burns says
highly creative stupendously low in
conscientiousness am I doomed no you're
not doomed and I think that openness and
conscientiousness are often at odds with
one another it is
obvious to me how someone can easily be
highly creative and orderly for example
because to be creative means to make
some disorder in the intermediary stages
of being a creative person I would say
also that many creative enterprises are
not the sort of thing that anybody who
was sensible from the perspective of
being conscientiousness conscientious
would ever pursue like the lifestyle of
a musician for example I would say
though that if you're low in
conscientiousness and really high and
openness high in creativity is that
you're going to have you're going to be
able to generate a lot of creative ideas
but you're gonna have a hard time
implementing them you won't have the
follow-through and you may have to
really learn to discipline yourself and
I would say the simplest way to start
disciplining yourself is to use
something like Google Calendar to
establish a schedule and and stick to
the damn thing like train yourself to
get up at the same time train yourself
to eat at the same time train yourself
to follow a schedule so that you
undertake the tasks that you need to
undertake each week on a regular basis
but but you can leave in that a little
bit so that it doesn't become
intolerable by using the schedule to
design days that you would want to have
instead of just days that you should
have because you'll doesn't have to be a
tyrant the proper use of a schedule
enables you to have the maximum amount
of freedom while also maintaining the
responsibilities necessary to stop your
life from augering into the ground so if
you're high and openness and and in all
likelihood you're fairly intelligent if
that happens to be the case and you're
low in conscientiousness you might be
able to get the best of both worlds by
learning to discipline yourself but it's
going to be a step-by-step process and I
would also say do something like the
Future authoring program from self
authoring calm and even if you do it
badly because one of the things that
will help you discipline yourself is to
have a plan and a plan is this is the
something that all of you who are
listening should know is like I really
recommend doing that future authoring
program because you you will not get
what you want unless you figure out what
it is you won't be of as much to use to
yourself and to the broader world unless
you develop a vision and implement it
and
the best way to do that is to do it
seriously and and one of the best ways
to do something seriously is to write
about it so my goal is to be married and
on my way to starting a family within
five years is this a legitimate goal to
have for myself well absolutely I mean
absolutely all of these things can be
made conscious I mean you know we have
this romantic belief I suppose that if
you open yourself up to opportunity then
it will ferret you out and your dreams
will come true but that's kind of a
naive way of looking at the world and
it's much more likely to be the case
that if you aim at something and and you
aim carefully and thoughtfully that
you're that you will orient yourself in
a manner that makes you aware of the
opportunities that will arise that will
put you in that direction that's
actually how your perceptual systems
work and so part of the reason that it's
so useful to orient yourself with
regards to a specific aim is that your
perceptual systems then turn on to tell
you what's going to facilitate your
movement forward and also what's going
to get in the way now you don't want to
be too single-minded about it because
you can get obsessive and you also want
to maintain enough flexibility in your
aim so that you can change them when
necessary but there's absolutely nothing
wrong with deciding not only you know
over what period of or during what
timeframe you might want to get married
and when you won't might want to have
children but what kind of partner you
want to have and what what sort of
interests you would like to share with
them and to really specify your life
because it's much more likely that it's
going to be turn out in a positive
manner for you and everybody else if you
put some intelligent thought into it
just like it's the case that almost
everything is likely to turn out better
if you if you do that do you suggest
homeschooling with the state public
schools are currently in no I don't
suggest it
I think homeschooling is an incredibly
difficult thing to pull off properly and
I think that there I think that the
number of people who would do it badly
far exceeds the number of people who
would do it well having said that it's
not like I think it's wrong and it's
also
like I think that there isn't increasing
reason for parents to consider that
because I do actually think there's
increasing reason for parents to
consider that because the postmodern new
Marxists have got their claws into the
education system and I think they're
doing everything they can and you can
certainly see that in in Canada in
Ontario where the Elementary Teachers
Federation of Ontario has published
they're there they're there
I think it's guideline curriculum it's
something like that that's basically a
blueprint for transforming kids into
social justice oriented individuals from
kindergarten through grade 8 so it's not
surprising that people want to do that
so but I think that parental rights
trump state rights in relationship to
children and it has to be that way even
though there's lots of bad parents
the thing about bad parents is that the
state as parent is worse it's not that
there are no bad parents but to assume
that the state is going to be a better
parent on average than parents who
actually know if their children is a
very bad idea so why is Jordan
Peterson's web cam a thousand times
better than all of my favorite YouTube
youtubers with millions of subscribers
because my son Julian who helps me with
technical matters bought a DL SML camera
DLSR camera for me that happens to work
extremely well except the battery runs
out about every hour and 15 minutes and
I have to change it so and I think
there's a there's it would be nice if I
could actually plug it in with an
adapter but I think that that changes
the category of camera to video camera
and then there's tax implications or
something like that so I have the high
quality camera and I have to put up with
the fact that the battery dies so how do
I plan to buffer myself from the
deteriorating side effect of success
that's a really good question actually
um I can tell you bunch of answers to
that I mean the first is is that I have
a sensible family a son and the daughter
and and soon to be a son-in-law and a
daughter-in-law as well who I like and
who like me and we get along really well
and they're really sensible people and
so they help keep me my feet nailed to
the ground
so does my wife because my wife is also
an extremely sensible person and someone
I really deeply trust and I'm also
fortunate in that I have parents who who
play that role with me as well and a
sister and brother-in-law and and my
brother as well who help me
stay attuned to the potential dangers
that this widespread public exposure
might otherwise produce but so but the
other issue so there's that I have
advisors let's say who are on my side
who tell me the truth and and we discuss
what I'm doing all the time to make sure
that it's staying more or less on track
the other thing too is though you know
I'm not exactly a young man anymore I'm
55 and I think a lot of the detrimental
elements of widespread public exposure
are things that would have been a lot
more harmful or that are a lot more
harmful to people when they're younger
there's just a lot of things about being
in the public eye that don't have the
same cachet to me that they might have
when I was a younger person or that they
would have to a younger person and I
guess I would also say that I don't
really believe that I'm the sort of
person to let and I'm not trying to put
myself on a higher moral plane or
anything with this comment but I don't
think I'm the kind of person to let the
sort of thing that's happened over the
last year or so really go to my head and
I think part of the reason for that is
that I have a fairly pronounced
depressive temperament and so that I can
see the negative side of myself with
with plenty painful clarity and I'm also
more concerned about the possibility of
making a catastrophic mistake as I
present my publicly than I am in what
clambering up some power ladder I
suppose and elevating myself to a
position at the top I'm just not that
interested in that and so I think and
I'm also I think fairly aware of the
dangers of of well let's say Fame to the
degree that that's what's occurred to me
I know the downside of that and it isn't
something that I'm interested in and I'm
actually I know it's a strange thing but
to think about but I'm actually also
rather private person and and although
I'm I can't keep my mouth shut obviously
and I'm very talkative that's from being
very high in openness even more than
being high in extraversion I think and
but there isn't anything that comes
along with the dark side of Fame let's
say that I would find particularly
attractive you know I'm not really
interested in partying endlessly
although I had my time doing that when I
was young I'm certainly not interested
in whatever additional attractiveness to
two females that my more well-known the
fact that I'm more my well-known might
provide to me that that just doesn't
interest me at all I'm very happy in my
marriage and also very aware of the
catastrophes that lie in directions of
that sort of temptation so but but I
also I think of all those explanations
the one that's most relevant is my see I
know that I'm walking a tightrope in
some sense and that it would be very
easy for me to make the kind of error
that would st. me and I'm I know that
there are many people who don't approve
of what I'm doing who would be very
happy about that and so I think also
living in a somewhat constant state of
existential terror about the probability
that this house of cards could collapse
is also something that keeps me oriented
in that humble direction and dwelling on
this a little bit but really is an
interesting question
I am also I believe I also have trained
myself so that I orient myself mostly to
considering what I'm doing wrong and
what I could be doing better than what
I'm doing right and so I'm always on the
lookout in all of the presentations I
make for where I didn't say things as
clearly as I might have and where I
could have
prove my delivery and so concentrating
on where what I have yet to attain is
also a good way of keeping whatever ego
boost there might be in more widespread
public recognition under control
having said that I'm very it's not like
I'm ungrateful for the fact that all
this has happened it's actually an
amazing thrill I mean things happen to
me all the time that are that are so
overwhelmingly positive that I can't
believe it so last night for example I
went to this restaurant called The Keg
and I go there because I have a lot of
food allergies and they're actually very
careful with people who have food
allergies and the waiter showed us to
the table and he knew who I was and he
said that he had been watching my videos
and that he had had four promotions I
think that's what he's doing he said
yeah four promotions in the last four
months at the cake and the reason for
that was that he had been watching my
lectures and decided that he was going
to adopt a more responsible attitude as
an employee and also didn't start
pushing the development of his career at
this at this restaurant and that worked
out brilliantly and like it was so
positive because you know I thought
about it as a true victory on his part
because he took the situation that he
was actually in so a real situation and
decided that he was going to maximize
the opportunity that was there for him
and you know there was nothing about
that that's negative it's all positive
and it's a personal story and he shared
it with me and I had some small role in
bringing that about and like that's just
an absolute thrill as far as I'm
concerned like every time someone writes
me and says I've been watching your
videos and I just decided to sort out my
life and to aim higher and that's
working it's just like it's such a
thrill for me to be able to provide that
service for hundreds of thousands of
people it's like it's a it's an
unbelievable privilege and I hope I can
figure out how to do it better and
better as I get more and more practiced
at it I mean that's really the aim and
with my colleagues
Daniel Higgins for example I have two
business partner Daniel Higginson and
Robert Peel Peale was my graduate
advisor at McGill and Daniel Higgins was
one of my graduate students
at Harvard and we've been working on
making psychological interventions
accessible to people for about 20 years
so they helped me develop the self
authoring suite for example we have a
whole host of psychological tools in
development including future authoring
program for high school students that we
want to bring to the broader general
public and so this public exposure also
gives me the opportunity to to make what
I know as a clinical psychologist and as
someone with some specialization in
technology especially through my
partnerships make that accessible to
perhaps millions of people I mean god
that's that's just an amazing
opportunity and so someone asks how do
you find the self authoring
autobiography outline well you go to
self are 3com it's available there let's
see
someone Annette Adler says I have also
done better in a lot of things due to
your kicks in the ass yeah well I mean
that's great
Annette I'm thrilled to hear that see
part of it you see the thing about
disciplining someone let's say is that
when you and I see this very clearly
what I'm talking to young people is that
I'm really on the side of the person
that wants to do something positive with
their life to make their own life better
because I think that's where you should
start you should start by making
maximizing the quality of your own life
that's not a selfish thing or if it is
it's the right kind of selfishness and
that you should figure out how to do
that in a way that's of benefit to your
friends and your family and your
community and you should take that
deadly seriously and the reason you
should do that is because that just
makes life better for everyone and it
reduces a fair bit of the misery that
would otherwise be part and parcel life
and it makes everything function
smoothly and one of the things I'm
really curious about is what the world
would be like if everybody decided to do
that because human beings are really
remarkable creatures and we hobble
ourselves very badly with deception and
resentment and revenge and the desire to
make things worse and arrogance and all
those all those sins let's say that that
that make us deviate from our true path
and our true path should be something
like imagine the noblest aim that you
can conceptualize and then sacrifice
your life to attempting to attain it and
there's nothing in that that isn't good
for everyone and so apart from the fact
that it requires a lot of responsibility
I just can't see why everyone wouldn't
do that and when I'm talking to young
people and you know shaking my finger
and saying you know grow the hell up and
get mature and take on some
responsibility I'm not saying that
because I'm an enemy of the person I'm
saying it because I'm the best friend of
the part of them that would really like
to walk in the light and and it's an
invitation to walk in the light and and
it would be remarkable this is what we
need to do as far as I'm concerned not
only in the West but in the world at
large but maybe in the West first is we
have to consciously decide that we're
going to do everything
we can as individuals to walk in the
light and to regard that as a noble and
heroic endeavor and to make that first
and foremost in our lives and that's
what we should be educating young people
to do and they can do that and so I have
dozens of people writing to me and
talking to me all the time who are
saying the same thing they're saying
look I've really been trying to get my
act together over the last six months
I've been trying not to lie which is
slightly different than trying to tell
the truth right it's a more humble goal
to not lie because you can tell when
you're lying but you can't necessarily
tell when you're telling the truth and I
I mean coming up with a plan and I mean
trying to discipline myself and I've
been cleaning up my room which is like a
nice humble act that involves
transforming chaos into order and they
write and say god things are just
working out way better for me it's like
whoa
do it man that's just you you keep that
up for 15 years and you'll be unbeatable
and that's what we should be convincing
young people to be is to be unbeatable
and not because that's what they should
do or because they're bad if they don't
but because there's nothing better you
can possibly do with your limited and
your limited and suffering bound life
than to aim high and and sacrifice
yourself to the attainment of those
goals so that's uh being a highly
creative woman I find myself fearful
that having kids will be spiritual
suicide hindering my endeavors but I
also don't want to have an unfulfilled
life can I have a full life without kids
well yes I I suspect you can although
it's risky Maddy because it's really
important for people to have kids
because the thing is is that you get
older than 40 and our culture is kind of
dopey in that regards it's it's
underdeveloped we live as if we live as
if we we only exist when we're young and
we don't it's like what are you gonna do
from the ages of say 45 to 90 or 95 you
need a family around you you need to see
your children girl you need to have
grandchildren it's a major part maybe
the most important part of the last half
of life now you said being a highly
creative woman I find myself fearful
that having kids will be spiritual
suicide well that's the part of your
question that I would really address
because I would say well don't let them
be spiritual suicide you know it may be
that there's a certain
amount of time that you need to take
away from the kids then this is the case
for parents in general so that you can
pursue your own creative endeavors its
children do not have to devour your life
in fact if you let them devour your life
then you'll hate them and you mistreat
them and so what you want to do is to
set yourself up so that you can have
children and have a life and that's
better for the children and it's better
for you like children can be taught
encouraged to spend a fair bit of time
not when they're infants obviously but
to spend a fair bit of time amusing
themselves that's especially the case if
you have more than one child because
they'll mutually amuse one another it's
actually easier in some ways to have
more than one child because with one
child you're constantly amusing the
child but with two or three then they're
off in their little you know Club
especially if you can stop them from
developing sibling rivalry that's too
intense and they can monitor themselves
so the trick is if you're a highly
creative woman this be disagreeable
enough so that you can carve yourself
out your own space so that you don't
come to resent your children and you're
afraid of that you're afraid that it
looks like you're afraid that if you if
you give yourself two children there'll
be nothing left for you and you know
that can happen if you have children who
have terrible health problems for
example but you can't protect yourself
against those eventualities in life
anyways but I would say your best bet is
to be a more selfish mother and believe
me I've had more clients who were ruined
by mothers who were too unselfish than
I've had clients who were ruined by
mothers who were too selfish so you need
to be there when the kids need you but
you shouldn't be there any more than is
necessary so let's see
Adam Watts as I feared having kids for
the same reason I'm a full time pro
artist you make your own normal send my
therapist JP is speaking the truth yeah
well that's the look that's the thing
you know
don't be thinking that you can't
organize your life when you have
children the thing about modern people
is that they're terrified of children
they and this because they think they
regard children as if they're miniature
tyrants and they can be of course
because anyone will tyrannize over you
if you allow them to perhaps not anyone
but virtually anyone why not regulate
your children's behavior I wrote a
chapter in my new book called don't let
your children do anything that makes you
dislike them and that's like really
serious advice is like if you allow your
children to conduct themselves around
you in a manner that makes you dislike
them if you're being honest if you're
paying attention to the shadow side of
yourself that can be aggressive and
destructive then then you're if you
allow your children to do things that
make you dislike them then they're going
to they're having children is going to
mess up your life but you don't have to
do that you're actually you actually
have a tremendous amount of control over
the quality of your relationship with
your children and also the manner in
which you choose to just disperse your
time and I mean you're you've got if
you're willing to think it through and
be clear you can be in charge of your
household the children don't have to be
in charge and it's not good for them to
be in charge anyways so people are
afraid of children and it's too bad
because children are absolutely
wonderful I mean you have to be careful
with them and they get tired and they
get hungry and they get hot and and they
don't have an attention span that's as
long as an adult who has a long
attention span but they're great company
and they're unbelievably comical and
they love you and like they give back
far more than they take if you have an
ounce of sense when you're dealing with
them so yeah so so don't be afraid of
children man you're you're the adult for
God's sake you've got the upper hand
and if you have a partner you can rely
on well then you know you can both
decide how it is that you're gonna run
your household so that you're actually
thrilled to death that you have kids and
that you have a life so all right let's
see
when am i appearing on h3h3 November I
believe November 3rd so I'm looking
forward to that let's see how do you
help someone with borderline personality
disorder that's Matthew Dodson
Matthew you know I'd like to answer that
question but it's so damn complicated
that I don't think I can manage it so
instead of doing a bad job even though
that's a very interesting question I'm
afraid I'm going to skip that let's look
back at the pigeonhole panel here do you
can
some people have criticized my portrayal
of post-modernism
in what ways would you claim you are
fair or unfair in your assessment of its
core principles well I've done my best
to to give it an even-handed assessment
and I think I'm unfair in that any
rather truncated criticism of a large
body of thought is liable to clip a few
corners but I would say that I'm
attempting to provide a snapshot a
relatively accurate but low resolution
snapshot of a certain kind of war idea
on a war of ideas that's currently going
on in our culture and that's primarily
centered in the universities and I don't
think my assessment of post-modernism
and its relationship with neo Marxism is
unfair in the least in fact I think that
the danger that's presented by that
combination of ideological of
ideological presumptions is more
dangerous than people are currently
aware of and that it poses a larger
threat to the integrity of our culture
then then I've currently stated it's
more widespread than I thought for
example when I first started speaking
out against post-modernism and neo
Marxism
I didn't realize for example that the
law schools had turned into it had
turned into training grounds for social
justice activists I didn't realize that
the legal system the legal training
system had become corrupt perhaps not to
the same degree as say the faculties of
education or social work but literally a
long ways down that road and so I think
I do believe that post-modernism is an
intellectually bankrupt school of
thought and I believe that its alliance
with neo Marxism borders on malevolent
and it may even go past the border into
actual malevolence because I don't
understand how anybody with an inkling
of historical sense can take a look at
the 20th century and then dare put
forward ideas that are derived from
Marxism as a as a treatment for any of
society's hypothetical
disorders and it's not to say that I
don't believe that there are that there
are errors in in in Western culture say
for whatever that's worth I mean
individuals make it more errors all the
time and groups make moral errors and
cultures make moral errors that isn't
the issue the issue is how are we doing
compared to any reasonable alternatives
what makes you think that it's it's
appropriate to compare the performance
of Western societies for example to some
hypothetical utopia of your own
fictional imagining especially when we
seen what sort of utopias have emerged
out of out of out of such imaginings and
what is it that you are offering people
as a concrete alternative and all I see
in post-modernism is destruction and
nihilism and always see in neo Marxism
is historical ignorant malevolence and
misdiagnosis well and ingratitude and
arrogance I mean the list goes on and on
so I don't feel that I've misrepresented
the post modernists in the least and I
find I regard like I've read a fair bit
of Foucault less of Derrida but enough
to get a pretty good sense of what he's
on about like Foucault is readable but
more or less obvious as far as I'm
concerned and so he's a third-rate
thinker and Derrida is just a
troublemaker as far as I'm concerned
although a very brilliant one and the
idea that the post modernists had that
there's an infinite number of ways of
interpreting any set of data let's say
that's actually happens to be a true
observation and a very problematic one
which is partly why it's it's so
difficult for example to evolve a system
that can that can visually perceive the
world and why about half our brain is
devoted towards that it's it's
definitely the case that coming up with
a viable interpretation of the world is
a very difficult process but but that's
about as far as the validity of the post
modernist claims go after that it's like
well yes there's a very large number of
potential interpretations of the world
but there's a very small number of
actually viable interpretations and
that's really what's relevant and
viability is constrained by all sorts of
of what would you call them well let's
call them constraints yes
you you have to interpret the world in a
manner that's commensurate with the
minimization of your own intolerable
suffering that puts very tight
constraints on which interpretations
you're allowed to bring forward you have
to do that in a manner that's iterable
and repeatable across time you have to
do that in a way that isn't too
objectionable to other people or even
better in a manner that what makes them
want to cooperate and compete with you
so that you know a rising tide lifts all
boats there's immense constraints on
organizing your perceptions in a manner
that is simultaneously individually and
socially highly functional and the post
modernist just just don't grapple with
that at all they and and they're they're
biologically ignorant beyond belief and
proud of that fact in any ways as you
can tell I can hardly say enough things
that aren't good about postmodern
neo-marxist there's there's apart from
the fact that they got the initial
observation right which is that there's
a very there's almost an infinite number
of ways of interpreting a finite set of
data everything else they've done is not
only intellectually bankrupt it's also
morally reprehensible and I think
they're corrupting our culture and I
think they're they're they're hurting
young people and they're hurting them as
well by getting them to pay for being
hurt which is really quite a malevolent
enterprise so I've got no what would you
call I have absolutely no regrets about
going after the postmodern neo-marxists
as hard as I possibly can and I'm
certainly not done doing so so one of
the things that's going to happen for
example in the next month or so I've
been working with a programmer who's
who's volunteered his services and has
already produced this he's produced a
website that enables people to enter
text that will then classify the text as
postmodern or non postmodern and so
you'll be able to enter course
descriptions from universities the
course description the professor's name
the discipline and the university it
will tell you the degree to which the
description is postmodern and then you
can decide for yourself
whether you want to take that and become
a social justice warrior if that's what
you think your education should be about
or if you should avoid that like the
plague that it truly is and so my goal
if I had to set a personal goal and this
is the sort of thing maybe that you guys
are helping me do with my continued
support on patreon is that I'd like to
knock enrollment in the postmodern
disciplines down by seventy-five percent
over the next five years I think that I
think I'm thinking about it from the
perspective of of non-violent warfare
it's that serious to me and that this
would be equivalent to cutting off the
supply chain it's like the the post
modernists need a continual influx of
young impressionable minds in order to
continue their propagandistic and
society devouring efforts and I'm going
to do absolutely everything I can to cut
that supply chain off at the source
hopefully and and reduce their
enrollment to the 0 that would match
their citation rate for their
publications so would I end my career as
an academic in order to enter politics
as a candidate for MP under Andrew
sheers leadership no I don't think I
would do that I mean I thought for a
while I thought at one point of running
for the leadership of the Liberal Party
in Canada and then I thought at another
point in running for the leadership of
the Conservative Party but both times I
decided that what I was doing as a
academic and I would say as someone
who's a Phylis philosophy philosophy a
philosophy and sign
Jesus it's been a long day guys I'm
starting to forget how to talk as a
philosophically and scientifically
minded psychologist was more useful than
anything I could likely do practically
in the political realm and I haven't
seen any reason to change that opinion
as a consequence of the events of the
last eight months or so and so although
I've always been interested in politics
as a potential career route every time
the opportunity has arisen and I've had
to make a choice between continuing what
I've been doing and pursuing a political
path
way I've always decided to continue
doing what I am doing and I think that's
probably what I will continue to do I
actually think I can have more influence
doing what I'm doing that I could by
doing anything else and that's partly
because I suppose if I thought there was
anything else I could be doing that was
more useful I'd be doing that instead so
that's the answer to that what is the
role of art in a healthy culture is
post-modernism as destructive and in
this domain as in politics well let lets
that's Michel Bamford well what's the
role of art in a healthy culture
well the artists articulate the the
artists are the people who first
articulate the unknown and so the role
of artists in a healthy culture is to
bring to public awareness elements of
being that have not yet entered the
collective consciousness so you could
imagine imagine that we're all living on
an island and many of us are in the
center of the island far enough away so
that maybe we can't even see the
shoreline and we can't see the ocean
that's that's where our borders and but
we're distant from the artists are right
on the edge and they're there they're
there they're expanding the landscape
they're there they're moving the culture
forward that's where my metaphor fails I
guess they're moving the culture forward
into the unknown and they do that by
translating what is as of yet
unimaginable but sensed into what is at
least imaginable and represented
represented in image and and drama and
literature and that's the precursor to
its full formulation in articulated
philosophy and thought and that's what
artists do their problem solvers their
problem detectors and problem solvers
that's what true artists do and they're
always trying to solve problems like if
you there's a great documentary that was
made about Picasso for example painting
and unfortunately I can't remember the
name of it I think it was made in 1957
it's available on YouTube and it's in
black and white and Picasso is filmed
making a painting on a on a window so
that you can see exactly what it's doing
and you can watch him work with ideas he
he
paint something in in any erases that
you know he paints over it then he
paints again and he paints over it he
moves the figures around on the canvas
it's a it's a windowpane as I said and
you can see them working out visual you
can see them working out problems and
solutions to problems using using his
visual imagination and the artistic
product the painting is is the
consequence of that rather than the aim
of it the aim is to formulate the
problems and to work out the solutions
and the artistic product the painting is
the byproduct of that not the aim and so
artists move us forward into the unknown
and you can see them doing that in
cities because it's the open people the
artists who go into parts of the cities
that are have degenerated to some degree
back into chaos and then revitalize them
and they civilize them and then the less
artistic people who who are more
conventional move in and you know that's
when you get gentrification and that
sort of thing and that usually chases
the artists out and they go somewhere
else
cheap and interesting and start the
renewal process again so the thing about
artists and it's a hard thing to balance
property in our culture is that artists
are unbelievably productive economically
but it's very very hard for them to
monetize their productivity so even
though what they produce can be of
incalculable value it's very difficult
for them to get any of the economic
value that they're produced actually
directed towards them it's a major
problem in and it's a major problem with
trade openness as a mode of being in the
world
so it's post modernism as destructive in
this realm as it is in politics
post-modernism is perhaps equally
destructive in all realms as far as I
can tell especially when it's a lot but
with new Marxism and those two things
there's no reason they should go
hand-in-hand you know because if you're
a post modernist there's absolutely no
reason stemming from your own philosophy
that you should allow yourself with a
new Marxist political outlook and the
fact that those two things are found
together almost inevitably indicates to
me that post-modernism is the handmaiden
of the neo-marxists rather than the
other way around
so in fact post-modernism is the
intellectual front that the
Marxists we're or a dog to hide from
themselves and other people their true
motivations which are mostly driven by
revenge and and resentment and the
desire to destroy and a hatred for
quality and a hatred for qualitative
distinctions which is deadly its death I
mean with young people you want to say
look there's not much to you're only
twenty and you're kind of useless but
that's because you're only twenty you
know it's that doesn't mean you're not
full of potential that potential needs
to manifest itself so that you can turn
into something that's that's a like
world-beating significance but in order
to tell a young person that credibly you
have to say look there are a true
qualitative distinctions between things
and you're just getting started there
are Heights that you can ascend to that
are genuinely high which also means
they're above where you are now but that
gives your life the fact that there are
those things to pursue gives your life
deep meaning and significance and gives
your struggle nobility and validity and
the postmodernist neo-marxist as far as
I'm concerned absolute enemies of
qualitative distinctions and so what
they do is destroy everyone's ambition
it's like we're already as valuable as
we're going to get it's like okay well
fine that's good we don't have to feel
bad about ourselves but what the hell
are we gonna do what are we gonna orient
ourselves towards what we want is
multiple hierarchies multiple steep
hierarchies of competence that are open
in in fair competition to everyone and
and if we don't have enough hierarchies
of competence for everyone then you know
it's up to the creative people to
produce some new ones it's not like
we'll necessarily run out so
all right have you ever had to tell
someone that they are best suited to a
subservient / blue-collar lifestyle
because they don't have any semblance of
brilliance okay well I want to take
issue with the formulation of that
question although I think it's a
perfectly reasonable question that's Jan
Swan don't be thinking that a
blue-collar lifestyle is necessarily
subservient I mean first of all you can
be a trades person and that's a really
good career choice as far as I'm
concerned it's it's very very valuable
in you know good plumbers are rare and
good carpenters are rare and good
bricklayers are rare and they're so
useful I mean I do a lot of renovation
work I've done an awful lot of
renovation work on all the places that
I've I've lived in and I've learned to
do a fair a bit of construction and
automotive bodywork and all those sorts
of things and I really like doing it and
you know there's their blue-collar life
is not necessarily subservient at all
because you can be master of your trades
domain and be unbelievably economically
useful and productive and creative and
independent and autonomous and so
there's there's nothing necessarily
subservient about that now you know if
you're thinking more about about let's
say life at the low end of a restaurant
but even there if you're a conscientious
person and you're careful and you and
you're awake and you treat the people
around you well and you do your job
properly there's also room for
advancement in the private sphere
there's no reason to assume whatsoever
that merely because you don't have the
intellectual horsepower to work well in
the ABS in that in the domain of rapidly
shifting abstractions that your life has
to be of secondary quality or or or
opportunity I don't see that at all and
and there is endless opportunity in the
trades and and I can in Toronto for
example there's a chronic shortage of
trades people and there's always a
shortage of qualified people for every
occupation so if I have to tell someone
that they're best suited to a
blue-collar lifestyle I wouldn't feel
bad about it I might save them a look
you know I'm you you know let's assume
you're talking to someone who has an IQ
of 100 which is the IQ of the average
high school graduate you might say well
look you know unless you're super
conscientious
a career in something like law is
probably not your best bet because
you're gonna be competing with people
who have IQs that are like 30 points
higher than yours or 25 points higher
than yours and if you really work
yourself to death you might be able to
main maintain competitiveness in that
domain but you're gonna be working at a
powerful disadvantage because the people
that you're competing with for example
are going to be way faster than you
verbally they're gonna be able to read
faster into reason verbally faster and
all of that and it might be better to
pick an ambition that's more in keeping
with the quality of your temperament and
your intelligence to put it bluntly so
that you can be but that doesn't mean
that your success has to be limited and
it also doesn't mean that I'm in the
elevating intelligence to to the
platform of the ultimate moral ideal
because the relationship between
intelligence and moral ideal is zero
there's no relationship between them at
all intelligence is a is a capacity
let's say that can be put to ill use
just as well as to good use and there's
nothing intrinsically better about smart
people they might be more useful for
certain things if they're oriented
towards the good but there's absolutely
there's no shortage of opportunity in
the working class end of the end of the
world and I can certainly understand
often why people might prefer that to to
the endless miasma you might say chaotic
miasma of complex abstract jobs one of
the problems with those sorts of jobs is
that you're never done you never
finished there's always more work than
you can possibly do so all right so
that's a good one
let's see here I feel sensitive to meme
culture slash irony it seems hard to act
out honesty when every facet of human
behavior has turned into a meme so I
worry people's natural reaction will be
to mock or scoff well you know I've been
the target of my fair share of memes
perhaps more than my fair share and I
actually find it extremely I'm really
happy about it and part of the reason
for that involves some of the elements
of our earlier discussion people were
saying well how do you plan to keep your
feet on the ground
say given your new phone public profile
and I see the the mean culture as part
of the corrective I mean there's a great
role for satire and irony and all of the
elements of comedy to to act as a
corrective and I mean I'd been fortunate
because most of the memes that have been
directed my way have been done with good
humor I'm lucky because for some reason
the ratio of positive attention I
received from the general public let's
say is compared to the ratio to the
amount of negative reactions I'm
receiving is very disproportionate I'm
receiving almost all positive reactions
so you know I'm in the fortunate
position of being able to laugh along
with it but I don't think that there's
any reason to assume that irony and
satire have to become cruel and scoffing
they they can be done with a light touch
and they can be done in a manner that
keeps everybody awake and make sure that
no one is above both criticism and and
and humor that they're now that sort of
thing can become cynical very rapidly
but it degenerates as soon as it becomes
cynical you see this with satirical
shows you know like I really like The
Simpsons the first 13 seasons in
particular and like it it was one of the
very rare true satires on American
television and it never degenerated into
cynicism in part because although it
comedic ly critiqued almost every
element of American life it was also it
also had a set of messages that were
very positive so for example the Simpson
family was an extraordinarily coherent
nuclear family unit and for whatever
homers faults might have been and they
were myriad he was always there as a
reliable and trustworthy father to his
family despite his you know somewhat
limited abilities both ethically and
intellectually he was there when it
counted and that stopped that show from
degenerating into cynicism and I also
think the same about the Trailer Park
Boys which is a show that I'm
have a fair bit of partiality for
despite its its endless profanity and
and an absurdity it has the same
underlying structure is that the
characters are bound together by genuine
affection and there's something about
that that that makes the satirical
message both positive and deeply
acceptable as far as I'm concerned so
I know lots of laughs Jordan watches
trailer park boys I don't just watch it
I really like it I really get a kick out
of it I don't know how many of you are
Trailer Park Boys aficionado is probably
not that many because it is a pretty
rough show but the conky episode that's
going to be one of them the high that's
one of the highest that's the the
highest reach of Canadian comedy as far
as I'm concerned that episode just
absolutely floored me it was so it was
so surreal and so absurd that all right
let's see here
what're is your advice for someone who
lives with chronic pain wow that's a
tough one how can I discipline myself
mentally in order to be productive when
I feel awful all the time
what coping mechanism posed by shivers
is like if you're suffering chronic pain
one of the things you can do is try not
to judge yourself too harshly man that's
really rough and why don't you start by
assuming that if you're having a hard
time disciplining yourself that it's
actually a consequence of the chronic
pain rather than a moral fault you know
like I've dealt with lots of people who
have had terrible chronic health
problems and you know you you you you
want to push yourself because you don't
want to end up in a situation where the
disease condition is taking more away
from you than it absolutely has to so
you attempt to impose minimal
disciplinary structures on yourself to
to push the illness back as much as you
can but if you're in chronic pain I
would say you need to find someone that
you can trust to talk to so that they
can help you plan and you need to be
able to delineate out what your
limitations are in a manner that they
can understand so that you can jointly
focus on how to make productive use and
high-quality use of the time that you
can actually spend outside of merely
suffering the other thing that I would
ask you about is are you sure that your
medication regime regimen is adjusted
optimally because antidepressants for
example can be very effective long-term
medication for chronic pain especially
drugs like celexa which so I don't know
if you use an antidepressant in your
attempts to manage your chronic pain but
that's something I would definitely
recommend and there's a lot of
pharmaceutical treatment and you know
you may have run the gamut already I
know lots of people who have chronic
pain have done that but and also
stimulants like the ADHD medications can
also be helpful in the management of
pain because stimulant medication has an
analgesic properties so you might want
to consult a number of specialists about
your medication regimen to see that
you're medicated to the optimal degree
but I would definitely recommend
antidepressants and also fine and and
talking to someone find someone you can
trust so that you can talk to them about
your genuine limitations and how you
might transcend them and and also see if
you cannot torture yourself with guilt
because you aren't able to live the
productive life that someone who's free
of chronic pain might I mean it can be
unbelievably debilitating so mostly well
so I'm very sorry to hear that that's
plaguing you and and when you say how
can I discipline myself I'm sorry I'm
afraid I've lost the question you you
said how can I discipline myself it's
something like how can I discipline
myself when I'm in in chronic pain it's
like well I think the more appropriate
question might be how can you ensure you
that you treat yourself with the
appropriate compassion if you happen to
be living with severe chronic pain and
maybe the disciplinary element should be
secondary it's something like that so
I'm getting tired guys so I'm probably
gonna stop at nine I'm gonna stop at
9:30 because I'm gonna start becoming
incoherent if I don't so just to give
you a warning we're gonna we're gonna
run this for 15 more minutes so it's
joining the military a respectable path
for my life well I would say it would
likely depend on how you conduct
yourself as a soldier it and also what
your alternatives are but I wouldn't so
I wouldn't say yes without reservation
but I certainly wouldn't say no without
reservation I think joining the military
can be a respectable pathway for your
life I mean it's obviously a complex
pathway but it's it's not like the
military isn't a necessity and so if
there's something in you that tilts you
in that direction then perhaps that's
courage in you talking that's certainly
possible so let's see
let's go back to the pigeonhole thing
here becoming a truthful person involves
dealing with the guilt of past lies is
it better to come clean about old lies
even if they will ruin lives or forgive
yourself and focus on living truthfully
in the present and future that's a
that's a really good question I would
say that there there are telling the
truth
doesn't mean saying everything about
everything all the time it's a lot more
complicated than that first of all you
have a right to privacy and second like
here's an example this is a tricky one
but I think it would address your
question imagine that you've had an
affair you have a happy marriage but you
had an affair and maybe you had an
affair three years ago and maybe it was
you know a couple of weeks or a couple
of months or maybe it was even only one
night and it's driving you crazy you're
guilty about it and you feel that you
should confess and I would say well the
first question is have you learned your
lesson and the lesson should be you've
processed what you've done and decrease
the probability that you will do it
again
to something as closely approximating
zero as possible and then you have to
ask yourself what makes you think that
you have any right to confess because
then what you would do is take the
original transgression which was quite
severe and hurt someone very badly by
revealing it and you might say well
you'll pat yourself on the back for
being a truthful person about it but I
would say you've already sacrificed the
right you have to be truthful about that
and and I know I'm oversimplifying it
because the only way to not oversimplify
such a thing is to use a real example
and not a hypothetical example but I
think many times the moral thing to do
is to take your guilty secrets to the
grave and maybe you can talk about them
with a therapist or you can talk about
them with someone that you really trust
who will maintain confidentiality but
you don't come clean about old lives
you're not coming clean about old lies
generally if that will ruin lives and I
don't think you
forgive yourself precisely and focus on
living truthfully in the future you
focus on living truthfully in the future
and perhaps you don't forgive yourself
exactly that doesn't mean you pound
yourself into the ground with guilt but
if you have done things in the past that
were reprehensible and that would
destroy lives if we're brought to light
then you should I think that generally
speaking you should do everything you
can to limit the spread of damage as you
attempt to move truthfully into the
future so you've said that a marriage
must be based on trust and transparency
and being shackled together how and for
how long should you get to know someone
how to set a foundation oh well you know
there's no there's no simple answer to
that
I think that you should know someone
well enough so that you can so that you
know if you can negotiate with them and
so that you have started to formulate a
vision of your joint future that you can
both look forward to with enthusiasm and
confidence so and of course that's going
to depend to some degree on your level
of maturity but that means you've
considered such things as do you have a
sufficient number of joint interests and
are you oriented in the same direction
with regards to how you're going to
handle your joint careers and the
possibility of children and the the
manner in which you're going to interact
with your in-laws and you you have to
start thinking about you have to start
considering your life together from the
perspective of practicality and
economics I would say so it can't just
be that massive erotic attraction that's
associated with with love although I
think that's extraordinarily important
and you're unbelievably fortunate if you
have that and you should do everything
you can to maintain it which and that
takes effort that takes real effort and
will but you need to ally that with with
maturity and intelligence and the
maturity and intelligence is okay we're
going to put our lives together what's
that going to look like at the level of
detail how are we going to handle our
finances where are we going to live what
are our joint plans going to be it
cetera one of the things that my
business partners and I plan to do in in
what would you say that in as an analog
to the self authoring suite is that we
want to develop an online program to
help people negotiate their
relationships and and so it would
actually provide an answer to this
question in a more comprehensive manner
is that imagine that if you want to set
up a household with someone then there's
a lot of things that you need to get
straight and you either do that by
bringing your unconscious assumptions to
bear on the situation and perhaps
clashing where they don't match or you
sit down like conscious and away
are an articulate couple and start to
negotiate what your joint
responsibilities are going to be and so
that would be well who's responsible for
the meals and when and what are you
going to eat and who's going to get
groceries and who's going to pay the
bills and who's going to do which part
of what household chores there are to do
and how is that going to be laid out
fair and so you should get to know you
should get to know the person that
you're with well enough so that you can
start discussing the real practical
issues of life and determine whether or
not you're capable of of negotiating
that and I don't think that necessarily
means that you should live together
because the evidence is actually quite
strong at least the last time I look
that people who live together are more
rather than less likely to be divorced
now that might be that might have
nothing to do with the actual act of
living together it might be that people
who are more likely to get divorced or
also those who are more likely to merely
live together but I don't think that's a
great solution for reasons I won't get
into now and with regards to being
shackled together is that that's a
complicated one and and I learned this
at least in part from reading Carl Jung
and the idea there is that unless you've
really made a commitment to someone like
a lifetime commitment and that that's a
serious commitment one that you're not
going to back out of you're not going to
take the relationship with a seriousness
that's necessary to make it of the
highest possible quality and
sustainability across the course of your
life and it's really important that it
is of that high quality and
sustainability because the relationship
especially when it starts to produce
children is a machine let's say a
machine that you jointly operate that
adds immensely to the quality of your
life and the depth of your life I mean
you you have the rope and strand of your
life and your partner has the strands
and the rope of his or her life and then
those are tied together to make a
stronger rope and then that unites you
across time and then you undertake
massive adventures together and some of
that is the establishment of a household
and the establishment of joint careers
and the maintenance of each other's
mental and physical health and the
maintenance of a high quality sexual
life and all of that very very Chao
to do all of that and then the joint
production end and care of children
which which sets you up properly for the
last half of your life so like I'm 55
now you know and both my kids just got
engaged in the last month so that's
pretty bloody amazing and they're both
setting up households and and they're
stepping into adulthood and I'm
fortunate enough to have them in the
city that I live in so hooray for me
that's so bloody fortunate that I can
hardly believe it I mean we've helped
them out and tried to make it what would
you say to make the possibility of their
living here be something that's viable
but I'm absolutely thrilled that they're
going to be around and I'm looking
forward immensely to having
grandchildren and like what else are you
gonna do when you're 55 you know and
you're gonna be 55 it's good I might
have 40 more years like what am I gonna
do with those years well so I have a
good marriage thank God for that and
that's partly due to the outstanding
moral quality of my life my wife who I'm
also extraordinarily attracted to and
you know we've built a life together and
we've had kids together and we're happy
with our kids and we had plenty of
struggle with our kids because one of
our children my daughter had serious
serious health problems which she seems
to have managed to resolve partly as a
consequence of her own brilliance but
you know we've set ourselves up now so
that our children are respectable and
mature young adults so thank God for
that and they've got partners who we
both really like and they're gonna have
children and well hooray
you know that means that this next part
of my life is going to be something that
I could invest into with with a fair bit
of hope and and and excitement and the
idea of having little kids around again
is thrilling because I really like
little kids they're really really fun
and so the the shackle together is more
like it's a it's it's it's such a I may
have even said that but it's such a
cynical way of looking at it it's more
like what you've produced is an
unbreakable bond between two beings and
that that makes both of them both of
them better in every way if it's based
on if it's a relationship that's based
on trust and genuine communicate
that's very difficult thing to attain
because you have to be willing to tell
the truth and the truth is DARAB
generally a horrible thing no I mean
it's easy to tell truth when everyone
wants to hear what you have to say but
it's very difficult to tell the truth
when no one wants to hear it least of
all yourself and so marriage gets a very
bad rap in our culture and so does child
rearing and I think that's absolute
catastrophe because really being in a
long-term relationship a marriage let's
say and having children that's
two-thirds of your life even if you're a
highly career oriented person that's two
thirds of your life and I'm a highly
career oriented person and my family has
been unbelievably important to me and
has also been something that's enabled
me to be a very effective in my career
because it my house has been a sanctuary
for me and thank God for that especially
over many times in my life but
especially over the last year so you
should you should get to know someone
long enough to know that you too can you
go tell the truth with each other
communicate and negotiate because the
most important part of a relationship is
the fact that you can tell each other
the truth and negotiate so how does it
feel to be viewed as a father figure by
many people who grew up without one well
I think it's an unbelievable honor how's
that and that is really what I think I
think it's a tremendous honor and I'm
doing absolutely everything I can to be
worthy of that and I would like to say
to all the people out there who grew up
without a father that's really too bad
because you need a father there to
encourage you that's what father's do is
they encourage they help make you
courageous and if I can help people
develop the capacity to be courageous
and to learn to tell the truth and to be
responsible then that's great I can't
imagine a better outcome for me and so
if people are willing to help me play
that role and to use what I've been
teaching to guide them in that manner
then hurray
I couldn't possibly imagine a better
outcome than that so
how do you formulate good questions
giving that a well given that a well
oriented question seems often more
critical than the answer that's a great
question by the way
a lot of what you do to formulate good
questions is listen like if you're
engaged in dialogue with someone and you
really listen to what they're saying the
all you have to do is notice when you
don't understand what they're saying and
then ask them for a clarification and
that's the case when you're dealing with
the factual world as well you know what
you do to formulate good questions is
admit your own ignorance to yourself and
then try to articulate that ignorance as
clearly and simply as you possibly can
and so I do that all the time when I'm
in my clinical sessions with people
because they'll be telling me the story
of their life years ago perhaps or maybe
events over the last few weeks or
whatever and they'll tell me the story
and I'll detect elements of it that I
don't understand or that are unclear or
that seem self contradictory and so then
I'll just ask it says well I don't I
don't understand what you're saying
there you said this as far as I can tell
but that wasn't clear what exactly do
you mean and so a huge and get them to
articulate it and maybe I'll say well
you said this now but you said this you
know ten minutes ago and as far as I can
tell those two things are opposites and
so how do you how do you bridge the gap
between those things and but the
critical issue with regards to good
questions is that you admit to yourself
your own ignorance and you're not
embarrassed about it like there's
nothing wrong with being ignorant well
that's not true it's a terrible thing to
be ignorant but it's inevitable but it's
not a moral flaw it's just unfortunate
the moral flaw is in refusing to admit
to it and so you know the students who
do really well in classes are the ones
who ask basic questions they put up
their hand and say look you know
everyone else here seems to understand
this but this is a point that I really
don't get and you know rarely a person
asks a question like that and they
haven't been listening and they haven't
been paying attention and they're just
being annoying but most of the time
people who do that have been paying
attention and they're asking question
that everyone else in the room would
also like to ask
is embarrassed to do so so all right hmm
you've said that positive emotion comes
from moving towards a goal but also that
friends and family are crucial critical
to a fulfilling life are both of these
hitting the same neural circuits I would
say no not precisely the the positive
emotion that comes from moving towards a
goal looks to me to be primarily
dopaminergic and the the positive
emotion that's associated with friends
and family I think is much more
associated with the opiate system and
some of the best work on that was done
by yak panksepp J a a K panksepp PA NK s
EPP and he wrote a book called affective
neuroscience and a variety of very very
good scientific papers and laid some of
the initial groundwork for understanding
the relationship between the functioning
of the endogenous opiates systems and
social bonding so no I don't think
they're the same there they share
overlap because the opiate circuits can
activate the dopaminergic circuits but
but there there are definite differences
in the system that that that seeks out
goals and that's the system that
panksepp actually called the seeking
system that's the dopaminergic system
and the more affiliative systems so
they're definitely overlapping but
separate neural circuits and so not to
take away from your interpretations but
for a skeptic how do you know that your
analysis of biblical stories are true
well that's a great question but the
issue there is what what do you mean by
true I would say they're functional
because I'm a pragmatist you know I mean
that technically I believe that our
conceptual structures are tools to help
us orient ourselves in the world and so
the issue for me is are the
interpretations that I'm making of the
biblical stories useful functional tools
for people to use to operate in the
world and how can I demonstrate that
their canonical interpretations of the
Bible
well I can't demonstrate that what I can
say is that people can listen to them
and make their own judgment about
whether or not they're useful and valid
which i think is a better way of
thinking about it then then true because
truth in literature and mythology is a
very tricky concept and especially in a
like the Bible which as I pointed out in
the first biblical lecture is the first
truly hyperlinked text where every
almost every verse interacts with almost
every other verse and so it's an end
it's endlessly deep and there's an
endless number in some sense of valid
interpretations that could come forth
from it but there's more to the answer
to that question but I can't go into it
for now because I'm what we're running
out of time and I'm running out of
energy in fact it is 9:30 and so and so
and my daughter has just showed up and
my wife has told me that so I think I'm
actually going to take this opportunity
to bow out and to say once again thank
you this is my wife by the way
might as well wear what I was watching
the video and I thought she was still in
the room the videos lagged so I was
actually interacting with a ghost there
for a minute um I wanted to thank you
all again for supporting me I also want
to say I know that for you patrons that
have been supporting me to the fore at
the $200 level I know that I promise to
give you producer credit on the biblical
videos and I haven't forgotten that I
just haven't done it yet because I would
like to say because I've been doing a
bunch of other things and I do actually
believe that's true but I haven't
forgotten and I still want to do it and
I think it is important and you have
been crucial to the production of these
this series all of you patreon
supporters and I'm hoping that I can
continue to put the support that you've
been offering me to to ever better use
and hopefully you can also help guide me
and doing that in these q and A's
because it gives us a chance to to
communicate so well so I'm going to say
good night and thanks a lot to all of
you and we'll see you in a month
get your act together all of you and and
do what you can man I'd be a wonderful
thing to see and if enough people start
doing that maybe we can turn this whole
mess around that'd be lovely and maybe
it won't take that many people to start
it so that'd be a good goal so good
night